A Guide to the Council on Foundations, Inc. records FA016
Rockefeller Archive Center
Council on Foundations, Inc. records
1949-1981
Rockefeller Archive Center
Council on Foundations
FA016
5.5 Cubic Feet 15 document cases
Arrangement note
The records are divided into three series:
Series 1 - Tax Reform Files, 1954-(1968-1978)
Series 2 - Commission on Private Philanthropy and Public Needs Files, 1973-1978
Series 3 - Miscellaneous Files, 1949-1981
The files within each series are arranged alphabetically by subject.
Biographical/Historical note
The Council on Foundations, Inc., incorporated in New York State in 1957 as the National Council on Community Foundations, Inc., was an outgrowth of the National Committee on Foundations and Trusts for Community Welfare, an informal association of community foundations in the United States and Canada based in Chicago. Initially, the organization's membership consisted solely of foundations of the community-trust type. Beginning in 1958, family, company, and other foundations were invited to affiliate with the Council. Also in 1958, the National Council was awarded a grant of $45,000 from the Rockefeller Foundation for exploring ways of expanding Council services as a clearinghouse for information and as a source of advice and guidance for members. Two years later, the Council received a $50,000 grant from the Ford Foundation to be used in assisting the Council in establishing itself as a national institution and in furthering its activities in the United States and Canada. In 1964, the organization's name was changed to the Council on Foundations, Inc.
The original National Committee on Foundations and Trusts for Community Welfare had a volunteer chairman, Edward L. Ryerson, a Chicago steel executive. Frank D. Loomis, a former executive director of the Chicago Community Trust, was the first secretary. With the establishment of the National Council on Community Foundations and the opening of offices in New York City in 1957, Wilmer Shields Rich became executive director, a post she continued to fill as the organization broadened its membership, until her retirement in 1968.
Following Rich's retirement, David F. Freeman took over administration of the Council in March 1968 and was given the title of president. The administrative structure of the Council called for a president whose role was defined as chief administrative officer. In this capacity, Freeman guided Council members through the changes brought on by the Tax Reform Act of 1969. Eugene C. Struckhoff, executive director of the New Hampshire-based Spaulding-Potter Charitable Trust, who joined the Council as vice president in December 1971, succeeded Freeman as President of the Council in1979. The following year he also assumed the role of chief executive officer.
The Council's dual top leadership structure was established when Robert F. Goheen, a former president of Princeton University, became chairman of the board and chief executive officer of the Council in 1972. The chairman's main responsibilities were policy concerns, public awareness, and Washington liaison. Goheen was succeeded by Landrum R. Bolling, a former president of Earlham College and of the Lilly Foundation, who held the positions of chairman and chief executive officer of the Council from January 1978 until December 1980.
In the spring of 1979 the Council relocated its offices to Washington, D.C. The move was intended to enable the Council to keep in closer touch with the many philanthropic organizations located there, as well as to improve its liaison with government agencies, the Treasury Department, the Internal Revenue Service, and members of Congress.
The aim of the council has been twofold: (1) to provide a common meeting ground and services for foundations administering charitable funds for public purposes; and (2) to encourage broader understanding of the community foundation concept of making philanthropy effective and responsible. The Council also represents the concerns and interests of grant makers to public policy makers, the media, and the general public.
For a more detailed discussion of the officers, operation, and membership of the Council on Foundations, see the Council history files in box 13.
Scope and Contents note
The records of the Council on Foundations, Inc., which span the years 1949 to 1981, cover the years from the formation of the Council until Landrum R. Bolling's tenure as chief executive officer in the late 1970s. The bulk of the material in this collection, however, concerns the Council's response to tax reform efforts in the late 1960s and early 1970s that would have profound effects on foundations. Also documented is the Council's relationship with the Commission on Private Philanthropy and Public Needs (usually referred to as the Filer Commission), a privately funded panel formed in late 1973 to conduct a study of the source, scope, and impact of charitable giving in the United States.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Related Archival Materials note
The following Rockefeller Archive Center collections include material related to the Council on Foundations, Inc. records: John D. Rockefeller 3rd papers; Rockefeller Foundation records.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
This small collection of records from the Council on Foundations, Inc. was transferred to the Rockefeller Archive Center in separate accessions in 1989 and 1991.
File Plan
Former Classification: X
Charities; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Philanthropy; Taxation -- Law and legislation -- United States; Philanthropy -- United States; Commission on Private Philanthropy and Public Needs; Bolling, Landrum Rymer; Council on Foundations; Struckhoff, Eugene C.; Goheen, Robert F. (Robert Francis), 1919-2008; Freeman, David F.
- Tax Reform Files, 1954-1978, bulk 1968-1978; bulk; 1; 2.75 Cubic Feet 8 boxes
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains correspondence, memos, policy and research reports, "Congressional Record" excerpts, press releases, news clippings, articles, and other printed material relating to tax reform legislation and its impact on foundations and on charitable giving. The Council's lobbying efforts, including its response to the Tax Reform Act of 1969, are documented in the correspondence of Council executives David F. Freeman, Robert F. Goheen, and Eugene C. Struckhoff with politicians, members, and tax consultants that will be found throughout the series. Approximately 20 percent of the Tax Reform Act of 1969 dealt directly with foundations. The act, which extended and intensified Internal Revenue Service supervision of foundations and helped eliminate what some perceived as abuses in the management of foundations, had serious effects on foundations and on philanthropic giving. Files in this series discuss the impact or potential impact of changes in such areas as net investment income, self-dealing, excise taxes, and income accumulation regulations. Information on Internal Revenue Code revisions and the effects of the Tax Reform Act of 1976 can also be found in this series.
  Also housed here are files that offer insights into the Council's relationship with Congress. These files contain copies of proposed legislation in the House of Representatives and in the Senate; transcripts of House Ways and Means Committee and Senate Finance Committee hearings; and correspondence with various members of Congress. Also included in the congressional files is a folder titled "Investigations of Foundations" (box 7, folder 61) that contains printed material regarding a number of congressional investigative committees, including the Special Committee to Investigate Tax Exempt Foundations (commonly known as the Reece Committee), whose chairman attempted in 1953-1954 to link foundations with the financing of communism in the United States.
  - Articles, 1967, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Articles, 1967, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Articles, 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Effects - Excise Tax, 1972-1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also Tax Reform Act of 1969 (Folders 37-41) and Tax Reform Act of 1976 (Folders 42-43).
  - Effects - General, 1969-1976, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Effects - Gifts to 501(c)(3) Groups, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Effects - Grants, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Effects - Minimum Distribution Rule (Ture Study), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Effects - Religious Groups, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Effects - Termination Tax, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Foundations - General, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Foundations - General, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Foundations - Lobbying, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - General, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - General, 1973, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Grants to Individuals, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Internal Revenue Service Code Revisions - Section 4944, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Internal Revenue Service Code Revisions - Section 4944, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Internal Revenue Service Code Revisions - Section 4945, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Internal Revenue Service Code Revisions - Section 4945 - Draft, September 28, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Internal Revenue Service Code Revisions - Section 4945 - Draft, November 19, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Internal Revenue Service Code Revisions - Section 4945 - Draft, December 21, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Internal Revenue Service Code Revisions - Section 4945 - Draft, October 7, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Political Activity, 1968-1971 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Proiposed Tax Law Changes, 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Proiposed Tax Law Changes, 1977-1979 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Reporting Requirements, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Subject Analysis - Accumulation of Income, 1963-1969 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Subject Analysis - Deductions, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Subject Analysis - Definition Problems, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Subject Analysis - Expenditure Responsibility, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Subject Analysis - Investment Income, 1969-1971 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Subject Analysis - Investments and Program-Related Investments, 1968-1971 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Subject Analysis - Limited Life for Foundations, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Subject Analysis - Self-Dealing, 1969, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Subject Analysis - Unrelated Business Income, 1964-1970 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Tax Reform Act of 1969 - Effects, 1969-1978 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Tax Reform Act of 1969 - Effects, circa 1971 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Tax Reform Act of 1969 - Effects, circa 1975 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Tax Reform Act of 1969 - Effects - Labovitz Study, circa 1972 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Tax Reform Act of 1969 - Effects - Lore Study, 1974, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Tax Reform Act of 1976 - Articles (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Tax Reform Act of 1976 - Effects, 1975-1977 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - U. S. Congress - House of Representatives - Bills, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - U. S. Congress - House of Representatives - Clay Brown Bill, 1966, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - U. S. Congress - House of Representatives - Cleveland Bills (H.R. 15847, H.R. 15848), 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - U. S. Congress - House of Representatives - Corman Bill (H.R. 11058, H.R. 1040), 1971-1973 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - U. S. Congress - House of Representatives - Emergency Home Finance Act (H.R. 17495), 1970 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - U. S. Congress - House of Representatives - Floor Debates, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - U. S. Congress - House of Representatives - Miscellany, 1959-1966 (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - U. S. Congress - House of Representatives - Nixon Proposals, April 1969 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - U. S. Congress - House of Representatives - Schneebeli Bill (H.R. 11197), 1972 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - U. S. Congress - House of Representatives - Ullman Bill (H.R. 13720), 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - U. S. Congress - House of Representatives - Ways and Means Committee, 1969, 1974-1976 (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - U. S. Congress - House of Representatives - Ways and Means Committee - Briefing, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - U. S. Congress - House of Representatives - Ways and Means Committee - Hearings, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - U. S. Congress - House of Representatives - Ways and Means Committee - Hearings Analysis, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 57)
  - U. S. Congress - House of Representatives - Ways and Means Committee - Members, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 58)
  - U. S. Congress - House of Representatives - Ways and Means Committee - Press Releases, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - U. S. Congress - House of Representatives - Ways and Means Committee - Staff Meetings, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 60)
  - U. S. Congress - Investigations of Foundations, 1952, 1954, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 61)
  - U. S. Congress - Joint Committee on Internal Revenue Taxation, 1959-1970 (Box 7, Folder 62)
  - U. S. Congress - Relationship with Foundations, 1974-1976 (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - U. S. Congress - Senate - Bills and Amendments, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - U. S. Congress - Senate - Finance Committee, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - U. S. Congress - Senate - Finance Committee - Hearings, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - U. S. Congress - Senate - Finance Committee - Hearings, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - U. S. Congress - Senate - Finance Committee - (Hartke) Subcommittee on Foundations, October-November 1974 (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - U. S. Congress - Senate - Finance Committee - Hearing, June 3, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - U. S. Congress - Senate - Floor Debates, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 70)
  - U. S. Congress - Senate - Muskie-Scott Bill (S. 3063), 1971-1973 (Box 8, Folder 71)
  - U. S. Congress - Senate - Statements and Contacts, 1969-1970 (Box 8, Folder 72)
  - U. S. Congress - Senate - Williams Bill (S. 2075), 1969 (Box 8, Folder 73)
  - U. S. Congress - Senate - Williams Bill (S. 2075), 1969 (Box 8, Folder 74)
  - U. S. Congress - Senate - Williams Bill (S. 2075), 1969 (Box 8, Folder 75)
  - U. S. Congress - Senate - Williams Bill (S. 2075) - Survey and Responses, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - U. S. Congress - Treasury Department Studies and Proposals, February 1969 (Box 8, Folder 77)
- Commission on Private Philanthropy and Public Needs, 1973-1978; 2; 1.5 Cubic Feet 4 boxes
  The Commission on Private Philanthropy and Public Needs (also known as the Filer Commission) was a 32-member panel formed in November 1973 to obtain information, analysis, and opinions on the function of private philanthropy in American society and its relationship to government. The Commission was established through the initiative of John D. Rockefeller 3rd with the support and encouragement of House Ways and Means chairman Wilbur Mills; Treasury Secretary William Simon; and former Treasury Secretary George Schultz. The chairman of the Commission was John H. Filer, chairman of Aetna Life & Casualty Company. Aetna, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, and the Ford Foundation each contributed $25,000 to get the Commission started. Eventually the Commission raised over $2 million to fund its efforts. The Filer Commission sponsored numerous research studies by scholars in disciplines such as health, education, religion, law, and sociology. This series contains correspondence between members of the Council and the Commission, as well as drafts of the Council's report and recommendations to the Commission; copies of a number of Commission-sponsored studies; and a summary of the Commission's final published report. (Both the final report, "Giving in America: Toward a Stronger Voluntary Sector," and the five-volume "Research Papers" published by the Department of the Treasury are available in the Archive Center library.)
  - Accounting Advisory Committee Report, October 1974 (Box 8, Folder 78)
  - Coalition for Public Good Statement, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 79)
  - Contributors List, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 80)
  - Correspondence, November 1972 - December 1973 (Box 9, Folder 81)
  - Correspondence, January-May 1974 (Box 9, Folder 82)
  - Correspondence, June-August 1974 (Box 9, Folder 83)
  - Correspondence, September-December 1974 (Box 9, Folder 84)
  - Correspondence, January-March 1975 (Box 9, Folder 85)
  - Correspondence, April-May 1975 (Box 9, Folder 86)
  - Correspondence, June-December 1975 (Box 10, Folder 87)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 88)
  - Meeting, January 15, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 89)
  - Meeting, September 10, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 90)
  - National Center for Voluntary Action Report, January 1975 (Box 10, Folder 91)
  - Publicity, 1973-1976 (Box 10, Folder 92)
  - Questionnaire, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 93)
  - Recommendations Comparisons, undated (Box 10, Folder 94)
  - Report and Recommendations of Council on Foundations (Rev.), August 1975 (Box 11, Folder 95)
  - Report and Recommendations of Council on Foundations (Rev.), August 1975 (Box 11, Folder 96)
  - Reports and Studies, October 1973-April 1974 (Box 11, Folder 97)
  - Reports and Studies, May 1974 (Box 11, Folder 98)
  - Reports and Studies, June-August 1974 (Box 11, Folder 99)
  - Reports and Studies, September 1974 (Box 11, Folder 100)
  - Reports and Studies, December 1974 (Box 11, Folder 101)
  - Reports and Studies, January-February 1975 (Box 12, Folder 102)
  - Reports and Studies, May 1975 (Box 12, Folder 103)
  - Reports and Studies, June 1975 (Box 12, Folder 104)
  - Reports and Studies, August-December 1975 (Box 12, Folder 105)
  - Reports and Studies - "A Consumption-Type or Cash Flow Personal Income Tax" (Andrews), April 1974 (Box 12, Folder 106)
  - Reports and Studies - Donee Group, c. 1974 (Box 12, Folder 107)
  - Reports and Studies - Federal Government Support for Education and Health, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 108)
  - Reports and Studies - "Giving in America: Toward a Stronger Voluntary Sector" - Summary, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 109)
  - Reports and Studies - "Guide to Sponsored Research of the Commission on Private Philanthropy and Public Needs", 1975 (Box 12, Folder 110)
  - Reports and Studies - "Public Funding Agency" (Larrabee), 1975 (Box 12, Folder 111)
  - Reports and Studies - Research Papers (Excerpts), 1977 (Box 12, Folder 112)
  - Reports and Studies - "Taxes and Charitable Contributions" (Feldstein), 1974 (Box 12, Folder 113)
- Miscellaneous Files, 1949-1981; 3; 1.25 Cubic Feet 3 boxes
  This series is divided into three file groupings:
  Council History
  Landrum R. Bolling Files
  Subject Files
  Material in each file grouping is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  This series is divided into three file groupings. The first, Council history, includes timelines and other material that document the formation of the Council (and its predecessor organizations) and its history. Also included in this section is material on the Council's proposed merger with the Foundation Center. The merger was discussed for a number of years prior to the recommendation put forth in the 1970 report of the Committee on the Foundation Field (also known as the Gardner Committee, after its chairman, John W. Gardner). The purpose of this ad hoc committee, which was formed in response to the Tax Reform Act of 1969, was to delineate and examine services and functions that needed to be provided to and for the foundation field; and to recommend an organizational structure for the field. Although the merger did not occur, the Council and the Foundation Center did work out a number of agreements, eliminating overlap and duplication of effort on the part of the two organizations. This series also includes correspondence, memos, and speeches of Landrum R. Bolling, chief executive officer of the Council, who wrote and spoke extensively on the need for a comprehensive public policy to encourage private philanthropy. An eclectic group of subject files concludes this series. Of note is a copy of the abovementioned Gardner Committee report (box 15, folder 131).
  - Council History, 1949-1979
    - 1949-1969 (Box 13, Folder 114)
    - 1970-1976 (Box 13, Folder 115)
    - 1977-1981 (Box 13, Folder 116)
    - Corporate Documents, 1957-1978 (Box 13, Folder 117)
    - Expansion, 1967-1973 (Box 13, Folder 118)
    - Foundation Library Center Merger, 1965-1966 (Box 13, Folder 119)
    - Foundation Library Center Merger, 1970, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 120)
    - Publications, 1977-1979 (Box 13, Folder 121)
  - Landrum R. Bolling Files, 1977-1980
    - Correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 14, Folder 122)
    - Correspondence, 1980, 1981 (Box 14, Folder 123)
    - Correspondence - Media, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 124)
    - Correspondence - Reading File, September 1980 (Box 14, Folder 125)
    - Memos, 1977-1980 (Box 14, Folder 126)
    - Speeches, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 127)
    - Speeches, February-August 1978 (Box 14, Folder 128)
    - Speeches, September 1978-January 1979, January 1980 (Box 14, Folder 129)
  - Subject Files, 1961-1980, undated
    - Alliance for Volunteerism, 1980 (Box 15, Folder 130)
    - Committee on the Foundation Field (Gardner Committee) Report, 1970, 1974-1975 (Box 15, Folder 131)
    - "Community Foundations in the United States and Canada, 1914-1961" (handbook) - Clearances (Box 15, Folder 132)
    - "Community Foundations in the United States and Canada, 1914-1961" (handbook) - Correspondence (Box 15, Folder 133)
    - "Community Foundations in the United States and Canada, 1914-1961" (handbook) - Production, 1961, 1965 (Box 15, Folder 134)
    - "Community Trusts of America, 1914-1950" (handbook), undated (Box 15, Folder 135)
    - National Awareness Program, December 1971-September 1972 (Box 15, Folder 136)
    - National Awareness Program, October 1972-November 1974 (Box 15, Folder 137)
    - Private Voluntary Organizations Consultation, 1979 (Box 15, Folder 138)
    - "Public Awareness of and Attitudes Toward Philanthropic Foundations" (Gallup Survey), 1976 (Box 15, Folder 139)
    - Vice President's Task Force on Youth Employment, 1979 (Box 15, Folder 140)